it's alan edelman and this little snippet will be
大家好，我是艾伦·埃德曼
about array basics so if you want to
这个短视频是关于数组的基础知识的
define a vector you can just go
所以如果你想定义一个向量，你可以用
v = [1,2,3,4]
v = [1,2,3,4]
and you can see that the size of v is four
可以看到v的大小是(4,) 注：注意这和(4,1)的Array不同。
however if you want an array one way to do it
但是，如果要声明一个数组，一种方法是写
here's one two three four five six uh
a = [1 2 3 4 5 6]
with a square bracket over here and another be here
一个方括号在上一行，另一个在下一行
and the size of w is two three so just to
w的大小是(2,3) （注：指两行，三列）
show off a few quick things you could do
接下来我展示一些简单的数组操作
if you want the upper left element
如果要让左上角元素
w[1,1] is one
输入w[1,1]，得到结果为1
if you want the lower right element
如果想取右下角的元素
it's the second of the third row you get six
是第二行的第三个数，w[2,3]，结果得到6
if you want the entire first row
如果想要取整个第一行
you can go comma colon which basically says take the entire first row
你可以写w[1,:]，这就是在取 整个第一行
and it'll come back as a vector
结果会以一个向量返回
or you could take the entire first column which also comes back as a vector
或者也可以取整个第一列,w[:, 1]，结果也将作为向量返回
a vector is one dimensional it's not um
向量是一维的
it's not like it's an n by one or one by n
而不是n * 1或者1 * n的
it's just a one dimensional object in julia
它是一个Julia中的一维物体
you could also slice through some planes
你也可以沿着某些维度做切片（Slice）操作
so you can take
所以你可以写
you could take two colon three and
w[:, 2:3]，沿着第二个维度做切片
you'll get a two by two array that comes out so
结果将得到一个二乘二的数组
now let's define a few arrays
所以现在让我们声明一些有趣的数组
here's a random matrix with the elements
这是一个包含随机元素的矩阵
chosen uniformly from one through nine
元素会从1到9整数中均匀选择
it's a three by four matrix
这是个3行4列的矩阵
so if i execute this a few times you see
因此，如果我多执行几次
i get different matrices but either way
可以看到我会得到不同元素的矩阵
the size of a1 is always three by four
但A1数组的大小永远是(3, 4)
okay here's some random pretty characters of various kinds
接下来看这里，这里出现了一些随机的漂亮字符
or interesting looking characters
它们看起来很有趣吧 O(∩_∩)O
so if i didn't have this pretty print
如果我不使用最后的pretty函数
which appears just below me
（这个函数就在下面一个代码块里写着）
you'll see it's kind of an ugly print
你会看到打印出来的东西就不太好看
well it's not terrible
的确，虽然没很糟糕
but it has those quotations and so the
但是这些引号看起来就很累赘
pretty print just kind of makes it look nice
pretty函数使它看起来更紧凑，也更好看
and it looks just like this
我们运行几次，看看结果长这样
so what we do is we're actually
所以我们做的实际上是
converting every character to a string
将每个字符都转换为字符串
and then just making it really look pretty
然后把它们连起来,最终得到这个好看的显示方式
i don't read this this was some magic that your ta shashi
我自己是看不懂这坨神奇代码的，它是你们的一位TA
once wrote, which turns makes it look nice
之前为了让结果看起来更棒而写的
but i'm not going to worry about that
不过我也不操心这个 ⊙▽⊙
here's some colors distinguishable colors of 100
下一个例子：这是一些可区分颜色的100种颜色
let's we can go a little slower
噢，或者让我们一步步来
you could take distinguishable colors of three
我们先选择三种可区分的颜色
you'll see we have three distinguishable colors
画面上就显示了三种不同的，很有区分度的颜色
or six so the idea is that there are colors in this world
参数改成6，就有了六种颜色。所以这其实就是生成了集中对比度强的颜色
that are quite contrasting to the human eye
对普通人的眼睛来说很有区分度
to the normal human eye and so
当然，是指对普通人的眼睛
these distinguishable colors you know like
所以，我们知道，用这些颜色来生成一张图
when you make a graph or something you're supposed to
或者做一些其他的事情
have very different looking colors so
会让这些图中的颜色很容易显出不同
here's a bunch of distinguishable colors
这是一堆可区分的颜色
and here's just some random
而这边下面随机生成了
10 by 10 array of these colors so every time
10 x 10的数组，每个元素都用上面这些颜色填满
i do this i get a different random 10 by 10 set of colors
所以每次运行时，我都能得到不同的一组组10 x 10的随机颜色
all right here let me here i just
好的，再来看下一个例子
downloaded the corgi
我刚刚下载了一张柯基的图片
um just took it off of a web page and
是从某个网页上下载下来的的
here i downloaded a snoopy
另外我下载了一个史努比的图片
and so here you see i could have a
所以在这里你可以看到我
random 5x5 array
可以生成一个随机的5x5数组
consisting of corgis and snoopy's and so
数组都是由柯基和史努比的图片组成
every time i run this
当我每次我运行代码时
it takes a little bit of time but you'll
虽然代码执行需要一些事件
see i get a different five by five array
不过可以看到，每次我都能看到一个不同的
of corgis and snoopy's each and every time
由柯基和史努比组成的数组
okay or here a little bit of code
好的，让我们来看接下来的一点代码
that's going to uh
首先，图中的这一段代码
i can copy the first matrix which is a bunch of numbers
可以让我复制出一个和A1相同的，由一堆数组组成的数组
and then put a one two three in the upper left element
然后在左上角的元素中写入123
or similarly i could take
或类似地
here i can take a five by five array of snoopy's
我可以在这里用史努比的图片填充一个5x5的数组
and put a corgi in the upper left element
并在左上方的元素中放置一只柯基犬
here's a multiplication table
下一个例子：这边是一张乘法表
this is what's called a comprehension in programming languages like julia
这在Julia和一些类似的语言中被称为“列表递推式”
so it kind of looks like math set notation we have i times j
它看起来有点像数学的集合符号，我们有i*j
for i equals 1 to 5 and j equals 1 through 5. this is a comprehension
其中i和j都从1-5遍历。这就是列表递推式，可以生成一个数组
you could do it with a double for loop like this one
当然，你可以用一个包含两个循环变量的double for循环来完成这个操作
but it's a little bit clunkier
但是它看起来就更笨重一点
people tend to prefer comprehensions when it can be done
因此人们在方便的时候，会更倾向于使用列表递推式
or you can even do it like in other programming languages where
甚至，你也可以像其他的编程语言一样，用双层嵌套的for循环来完成这件事
you really have just the nested loops
确实，嵌套循环也是可以用的
but again the comprehension is much much nicer
但，列表递推式真的是更好的选择
so people tend to like that
人们也更倾向于用它
if you just square an array
接下来看下一个例子：如果你只是对一个数组求平方(A^2)
you get the the matrix times itself
你得到矩阵乘以本身
however if you do point square
不过如果你用"点平方" (A.^2)
you get the element-wise square okay
你会得到每个元素求平方之后的结果
you can also concatenate matrices by just
您也可以通过将矩阵放在方括号中并排
putting them next to each other in square brackets
来拼接它们
and so here's [A4 A4] which is double the number of columns that a4 had
所以如果写[A4 A4]，那么就会把A4的列数增加一倍
and what you can also vertically concatenate with semicolon
当然，你还可以用分号将数组在垂直方向上拼接
semicolon and so you get [A3; A3] gives you exactly that
所以如果写[A3;A3], 就会得到如图所示的结果 A3在垂直方向重复出现了两次
right you could kind of combine these and
你当然可以同时使用水平拼接和数值拼接
you know horizontally and vertically concatenate
如图所示，就是这样
okay that's it for basic arrays thank you
好的，以上就是基本的一些矩阵操作，谢谢大家！